# **Neeraj Varshney**

Ph.D. Candidate ( $4^{th}$  Year) Computer Science (NLP/NLU) Arizona State University Email: nvarshn2@asu.edu Website: <u>nrjvarshney.github.io</u> Semantic Scholar: <u>Neeraj-Varshney</u> LinkedIn: <u>neerajvarshney97</u>

## RESEARCH STATEMENT

I work in Natural Language Processing, primarily in the areas of Open-domain QA, Natural Language Inference, Retrieval augmented inference, addressing different Efficiency & Reliability aspects of NLP systems, and Natural Language Understanding in general.

On the efficiency topic, I have worked on improving inference efficiency, training sample efficiency, QA reader efficiency, knowledge indexing efficiency, and evaluation efficiency. Furthermore, on the reliability topic, I have worked on selective prediction, post-abstention, calibration, and mitigating model hallucinations.

Publication Venues: ACL EMNLP EACL NAACL AAAI AAMAS.

**Research Interests**: Efficiency and Reliability aspects in NLP

**Open-domain Question Answering** 

Robustness

Retrieval-Reader Systems Multi-task Learning

**Learning From Natural Language Instructions** 

Selective Prediction Generalization

Mitigating Model Hallucinations Learning From Less Supervision

Thesis Committee: Dr. Chitta Baral (Chair)

Dr. Yezhou Yang Dr. Nakul Gopalan Dr. Pratyay Banerjee

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Languages** : Python, Java, C, C++

**Frameworks** : PyTorch, PyTorch-lightning

Libraries : Huggingface Transformers, Spacy, Pyserini, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, NLTK, Word2vec

**Tools** : Git, Linux, Amazon Mechanical Turk, PyCharm, Jupyter, Colab, MS Office

## **SELECTED PROJECTS**

## On Efficiently Indexing External Knowledge for Open-QA

**Under Review** 

# Can Open-Domain QA Reader Utilize External Knowledge Efficiently like Humans?

AAAI @ KnowledgeNLP 2023

N. Varshney, M. Luo, C. Baral

- Studied an approach that utilizes both the 'closed-book' (parametric knowledge) and the 'open-book' (external knowledge) inferences in an efficient manner.
- Instead of using a large fixed number of passages for open-book inference, the system dynamically reads the external knowledge in multiple 'knowledge iterations'.
- Comparing with the Fusion-in-Decoder (FiD) reader, our approach matches FiD's accuracy by utilizing just 18.32% of its reader inference cost (FLOPs) and also outperformed it by achieving up to 55.10% and 77.32% accuracy on NQ Open and TriviaQA respectively.

# **Unsupervised Natural Language Inference Using PHL Triplet Generation**

ACL, 2022

N. Varshney, P. Banerjee, T. Gokhale, C. Baral

- Designed three novel unsupervised settings for NLI and proposed a procedural data generation approach that outperforms existing approaches by  $\sim \! 13\%$  and raises the SOTA unsupervised performance to 66.75%.
- Also proposed a model-in-the-loop adversarial data collection strategy to efficiently collect high-quality non-trivial data instances that help achieve 12.2% higher accuracy with as little as  $\sim 0.1\%$  of the training dataset.

# Investigating Selective Prediction Approaches Across Several Tasks in IID, OOD, and Adversarial Settings ACL, 2022

N. Varshney, S. Mishra, C. Baral

- Systematically studied 'selective prediction' in a large-scale setup of 17 datasets across NLI, QA, and Duplicate Detection tasks under in-domain, out-of-domain, and adversarial settings.
- Showed that despite leveraging additional resources (held-out data/computation), none of the existing approaches consistently and considerably outperforms a simple *MaxProb* baseline.
- Evaluated several approaches on their task-transfer ability.

## **ILDAE: Instance-Level Difficulty Analysis of Evaluation Data**

ACL, 2022

N. Varshney, S. Mishra, C. Baral

- Computed instance-level difficulty scores for evaluation instances and demonstrated their five novel applications:
  - Conducting efficient-yet-accurate evaluations with fewer instances saving computational cost and time,
  - Improving the quality of existing evaluation datasets by repairing erroneous and trivial instances,
  - Selecting the best model based on application requirements,
  - Analyzing dataset characteristics for guiding future data creation,
  - Estimating Out-of-Domain performance reliably.

# Post-Abstention: Towards Reliably Re-Attempting the Abstained Instances in QA

ACL, 2023

N. Varshney, C. Baral

• Post-Abstention aims at re-attempting the abstained instances of a given selective prediction system with the aim of increasing its 'coverage' without significantly sacrificing its 'accuracy'.

## **NumGLUE: A Suite of Mathematical Reasoning Tasks**

ACL, 2022

- S. Mishra, A. Mitra, N. Varshney, B. Sachdeva, P. Clark, C. Baral, A. Kalyan
- Proposed a multi-task benchmark that evaluates AI systems on eight different numerical understanding tasks and evaluated neural models including large language models.
- Proposed a knowledge-retrieval based multi-task learning method that outperforms existing models.

## **Towards Improving Selective Prediction Ability of NLP Systems**

ACL @ RepL4NLP, 2022

N. Varshney, S. Mishra, C. Baral

- Proposed a method that improves over MaxProb by calibrating the model outputs using prediction confidence and difficulty level of the instances.
- Instantiated the proposed method in NLI and Duplicate Detection tasks and showed that it outperforms existing approaches and achieves up to 15% improvement over MaxProb.

# Model Cascading: Towards Jointly Improving Inference Efficiency and Accuracy of NLP Systems

EMNLP, 2022

N. Varshney, C. Baral

• Proposed a technique that utilizes a collection of models of varying capacities to accurately yet efficiently output predictions.

## Benchmarking Generalization via In-Context Instructions on 1,600+ Language Tasks

EMNLP, 2022

Y. Wang, ..., N. Varshney, ..., C. Baral, Y. Choi, N. Smith, H. Hajishirzi1, D. Khashabi

- Introduced Super-NaturalInstructions, a benchmark of 1,616 diverse NLP tasks and their expert-written instructions.
- Built Tk-Instruct, a transformer model trained to follow a variety of in-context instructions (plain language task definitions or k-shot examples).

# A Unified Evaluation Framework for Novelty Detection and Accommodation in NLP

ACL, 2023

N. Varshney, H. Gupta, E. Robertson, B. Liu, C. Baral

# On Dealing with Questions that Don't have Definitive Answers

ACL @ TrustNLP, 2023

N. Varshney\*, A. Agarwal\*, N. Patel\*, M. Parmar, ..., and C. Baral

## On Evaluating NLP Models' Understanding of Feasibility

EACL, 2023

H. Gupta, N. Varshney, S. Mishra, K. Pal, S. Sawant, K. Scaria, S. Goyal, C. Baral

- Introduced FeasibilityQA, a question-answering dataset involving binary classification and multi-choice multi-correct questions that test understanding of feasibility.
- Highlighted that even state-of-the-art models such as GPT-3 struggle to answer the feasibility questions correctly.

# Let the Model Decide its Curriculum for Multitask Learning

NAACL @ DeepLo, 2022

- Proposed dataset and instance-level techniques to arrange training instances into a learning curriculum based on the model's own interpretation of difficulty.
- Achieved 4% accuracy improvement over other methods on experiments conducted for 12 datasets covering a variety of language understanding tasks.

# An Architecture for Novelty Handling in a Multi-Agent Stochastic Environment

AAAI Sym. 2022

T. Thai, M. Shen, N. Varshney, S. Gopalakrishnan, U. Soni, M.Scheutz, C. Baral, J. Sinapov

• Introduced an architecture that allows agents to detect novelties, characterize those novelties, and build an appropriate adaptive model to accommodate them.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Tencent AI**NLP Research Intern
Bellevue, Washington

Amazon ScienceMay 2022 – Aug 2022Applied Scientist InternSeattle, Washington

• Web Question-Answering System for Alexa AI.

MicrosoftJuly 2018 – Aug 2019Software DeveloperBangalore, India

• Worked towards developing a machine learning driven chat recommendation system aimed at augmenting user engagement with the product Microsoft 'Teams'.

Samsung R&D InstituteSummer 2017Research InternBangalore, India

• Developed a 'context prediction' application incorporating features based on device events (e.g app usage, location) and sensor data (proximity sensor).

## **EDUCATION**

#### **Arizona State University**

Tempe, AZ, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Aug 2019 - Spring 2024 (Expected)

• Advisor: Dr. Chitta Baral

• CPGA: 4/4

- **Awards**: SCAI doctoral fellowship, <u>GPSA</u> awards (3 times), <u>SCAI conference</u> award (2 times), <u>Graduate College</u> awards (5 times), <u>AAAI student scholarship</u>, <u>ACL registration award</u>.
- Internships: Amazon Science (Summer 2022), Tencent AI (Summer 2023)

# BITS Pilani, Pilani Campus, India

Pilani, India 2014-2018

B.E (Hons) Computer Science

• CGPA: 9.11/10 (with Distinction)

- **Experience**: 'Web Intelligence & Social Computing' research lab under Prof. Poonam Goyal, CEERI research lab under Dr. J.L. Raheja.
- Internships: Microsoft, Samsung R&D Institute, Valuefirst Digital Media.

# **HONORS AND AWARDS**

- SCAI Doctoral Fellowship, School of Computing and AI at ASU, 2023.
- AAAI Student Scholarship, 2023
- Graduate College Travel Award, ASU for AAAI 2023, ACL 2022, NAACL 2022, EMNLP 2022, and ACL 2023.
- GPSA Travel Award, ASU for EMNLP 2022 and ACL 2022.
- SCAI Conference Award, ASU for EMNLP 2022 and ACL 2022.
- Registration award from Repl4NLP for ACL, 2022.
- GPSA Internship Travel Award, ASU 2023.

## **SERVICE**

- Reviewer for ACL'23 (Question Answering track).
- · Reviewer for EMNLP'23.
- · Reviewer for EACL'23 (Question Answering track).
- Reviewer for CVPR workshop (Open-Domain Retrieval Under a Multi-Modal Setting) 2022 and 2023.
- Mentored B.S and M.S students for class projects and co-authored multiple research papers.
- Served as Maths and Science teacher for underprivileged kids in National Service Scheme (NSS).
- · Member of blood donation camps and health awareness drives.

# **COURSES**

- · Natural Language Processing
- · Statistical Machine Learning
- Artificial Intelligence
- · NLP Methods in BioMedical
- Knowledge Representation
- · Data Mining
- · Social Media Mining
- Mobile Computing

## **COLLABORATORS**

- Swaroop Mishra (Research Scientist at Google Brain)
- Pratyay Banerjee (Applied Scientist at Alexa AI, Amazon Science)
- Hongming Zhang (Senior Research Scientist at Tencent AI)
- Wenlin Yao (Senior Research Scientist at Tencent AI)
- Tejas Gokhale (Assistant Professor at University of Maryland, Baltimore County)
- Man Luo (ASU)
- Arindam Mitra (Data and Applied Scientist at Microsoft Research)
- Daniel Khashabi (Allen AI, Assistant Professor at Johns Hopkins University)
- Bing Liu (Professor at University of Illinois at Chicago)
- Ashwin Kalyan (Allen AI)
- Yizhong Wang (Allen AI, University of Washington)
- Rik Koncel-Kedziorski (Alexa AI)
- Eric Robertson (PAR Government)
- Mihir Parmar (ASU)

## **OTHERS**

- Published 20+ ML/NLP-related articles on medium with 80,000+ views.
- Worked with Dr. Ayush Choure and Dr. Prateek Jain (MSR, India)
- Campus Coordinator of Computer Science Association at BITS Pilani and organized numerous on-campus events, such as Alumni Research Talks and Technical Fest competitions.